<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Guillaume's Blog</title>
 <link href="/perso/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/perso/"/>
 <updated>2015-01-30T23:45:43+01:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Guillaume Lobet</name>
   <email>guillaume.lobet@ulg.ac.be</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The story behind the papers</title>
   <link href="/perso//2015/01/27/story-behind-papers.html"/>
   <updated>2015-01-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/01/27/story-behind-papers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/story_behind/iceberg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the publishing iceberg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Image credit: Pere, &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pere/523019984/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published papers are only the tip of the research iceberg. The visible part is often a fraction of the results acquired over the years while the hidden part is made of sweat and perseverance. Of repeated cycles of failures and success. Of (lonely) hours in the lab or in front of a computer. Of writing, submitting, re-writing, re-submitting. The hidden part is where the people (we, as scientists) are. So, often, when I read a paper I wonder about the story behind the project. When did it start and how long did it take to achieve it all? Why did they choose such approach? In short, what is the story behind this paper?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, recently, I remembered the &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylogenomics.blogspot.be/&quot;&gt;Tree of Life&lt;/a&gt; blog, written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/+JonathanEisen/posts&quot;&gt;Jonathan Eisen&lt;/a&gt;. The blog features a &lt;a href=&quot;http://phylogenomics.blogspot.be/p/story-behind-paper-series.html&quot;&gt;Story behind the paper&lt;/a&gt; section, which I always found great. Written by Jonathan Eisen or invited contributors, each post is a about a recently (or not) published paper and brings a more human view of the research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, my writing skills and publication record are far more modest than J. Eisen’s. But I figured I might take his example and write about the story behind my own papers. I believe the scientific process is, in most case, as important as the results. From an educational point of view, it is crucial for futures scientist to understand how science is made so they can choose this path in full understanding of what lies ahead.  I hope it will be useful to someone. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2015/01/27/story-behind-papers.html&amp;amp;text=The story behind the papers&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Impactstory Advisor of the Month</title>
   <link href="/perso//2014/09/19/impactstory.html"/>
   <updated>2014-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2014/09/19/impactstory</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;message&quot;&gt;
This interview was originally posted by Stacy Konkiel on http://blog.impactstory.org/].
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guillaume is a post-doc researcher at the Université de Liège in Belgium, in the Plant Physiology lab of Pr. Claire Perilleux. He’s also a dedicated practitioner of open, web native science, creating awesome tools ranging from a Plant Image Analysis software finder to an image analysis toolbox that allows the quantitative analysis of root system architecture. He’s even created an open source webapp that uses Impactstory’s open profile data to automatically create CVs in LaTeX, HTML, and PDF formats. (More on that below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of corresponding with Guillaume this week to talk about his research, what he enjoys about practicing web native science, and his approach to being an Impactstory Advisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tell-us-a-bit-about-your-current-research&quot;&gt;Tell us a bit about your current research.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a plant physiologist. My current work focuses on how the growth and development of different plant organs (e.g. the root and the shoot) are coordinated, and how modifications in one organ affects the others. The project is fascinating, because so far the majority of the plant research is focused on one specific organ or process and few has been done to try to understand how the different parts communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-you-initially-decide-to-join-impactstory&quot;&gt;Why did you initially decide to join Impactstory?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I created a website referencing the existing plant image analysis software tools (www.plant-image-analysis.org). I wanted to help users understand how well the tools (or more specifically, the scientific papers describing the tools) have been received by the community. At that time, an article-level Impactstory widget was available, and I choose to use it. It was a great addition to the website!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I created a Impactstory profile and I’ve used it since then. (A quick word about the new profiles: they look fantastic!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-you-decide-to-become-an-advisor&quot;&gt;Why did you decide to become an Advisor?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly because the ideas promoted by the Impactstory team are in line with my own. Researchers’ contributions to the scientific community (or even to society in general) are not only done by publishing peer-reviewed paper (even though it is still a very important way to disseminate our findings). The Web 2.0 brought us a large array of means to contribute to the scientific debate and it would be restrictive not to consider those while evaluating one’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-have-you-been-spreading-the-word-about-impactstory&quot;&gt;How have you been spreading the word about Impactstory?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by talking about it with my direct colleagues. Then, I noticed that science valorisation in general was not well known, so made a presentation about it and shared it on Figshare. To my great surprise, it became my most viewed item (I guess people liked the Lord of the Rings / Impactstory mash up :)). In addition, I also created a small widget to convert any Impactstory online profile into a resume. And of course, I proudly wear my Impactstory t-shirt whenever I go to conferences, which alway bring questions such as “I heard of that, what is it exactly?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youre-a-web-native-scientist-as-evidenced-by-your-active-presence-on-sites-like-figshare-github-and-mendeley-when-did-you-start-practicing-web-native-science-what-do-you-like-about-it-are-there-drawbacks&quot;&gt;You’re a web-native scientist (as evidenced by your active presence on sites like Figshare, Github, and Mendeley). When did you start practicing web-native science? What do you like about it? Are there drawbacks?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really started a couple of years ago, by the end of my PhD. At that time, I needed to apply for a new position, so I set up a webpage, Mendeley account, and so on. I quickly found it to be a great way to get in touch with other researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I like the most about web-native science is that boundaries are disappearing! You do not need to meet people in person to build a new project or start a new collaboration. It brings together all the researchers of the same fields who are scattered around the globe, into a small digital community where they can easily interact!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of the drawbacks, I am still looking for them :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tell-us-about-your-impact-cv-webapp-which-converts-anyones-impactstory-profile-data-into-pdf-markdown-latex-or-html-format-whyd-you-create-it-and-howd-you-do-it&quot;&gt;Tell us about your “Impact CV” webapp, which converts anyone’s Impactstory profile data into PDF, Markdown, LaTeX, or HTML format. Why’d you create it and how’d you do it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I needed to update my resume and my IS profile contained all my research outputs. So I thought it would be nice to be able to reuse this information, not only for me, but for everyone who has an Impactstory profile. So instead of copying &amp;amp; pasting my online profile to my resume,  I took advantage of the openness of Impactstory to automatically retrieve the data contained in my profile (everything is stored in a Json file that is readily available from any profile) and re-use it locally. I wrapped it up in a webpage (http://www.guillaumelobet.be/impact) and Voilà!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-the-best-part-about-your-work-as-a-post-doc-researcher-at-the-universit-de-lige&quot;&gt;What’s the best part about your work as a post-doc researcher at the Université de Liège?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic freedom is definitely the best part about working in a University. It gives us the latitude to explore unexpected paths. And I work with great people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2014/09/19/impactstory.html&amp;amp;text=Impactstory Advisor of the Month&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Root image analysis papers</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/08/12/image-analysis-papers.html"/>
   <updated>2012-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/08/12/image-analysis-papers</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not all papers on root image analysis present a new software and therefore I do not present them on this website. However, some of them are worth reading since they can bring new perspectives or methods that can be useful for all root researchers. So in order to be able to share all the interesting papers I read on root image analysis, I decide to create a group on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mendeley.com&quot;&gt;Mendeley website&lt;/a&gt; (Mendeley is a free citation manager with several sharing and social features). I am therefore delighted to invite you to consult or even join this group and hope it will turn out to be useful for everyone interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 820px;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.mendeley.com/groups/2469541/root-image-analysis/widget/17/10/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/08/12/image-analysis-papers.html&amp;amp;text=Root image analysis papers&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using a camera to take vertical root pictures</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/06/16/picture-vertical-camera.html"/>
   <updated>2012-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/06/16/picture-vertical-camera</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One way to take root picture using a camera is just to hold your root system by the collar and take a picture. While this technique might be the fastest and the easiest one, it is also to easiest way to get a bad picture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a couple of things to think of before taking such image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use young plants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose the proper camera and lens (A)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always place the camera at the same distance of the roots (B)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a dark, matt background (C)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place a scale on the background (D)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/camera_vertical.png&quot; alt=&quot;vertical camera&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the root system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large root systems are not suitable for such pictures. Because they have a lot of roots, they will probably be stuck together, and you will be unable the take any picture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the camera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose a camera with a high-resolution. If the resolution if too low, the number of pixels contained in the roots will be too low to extract any information. In order to increase the resolution, it is also possible to take the picture closer to the roots, but his will need an adequate lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose a background with a color different from the root (usually black is working well). Also be careful not the choose a “shiny” background, as it can create noise in the last image which can impedes the later analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the image scale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you take a picture with a camera, its scale (pixels/cm) will change if the distance between the object and the camera changes. It is therefore important that an object of a known size is present in the picture to scale your image during the image processing steps.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/06/16/picture-vertical-camera.html&amp;amp;text=Using a camera to take vertical root pictures&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using a scanner to take root pictures</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/06/16/picture-scanner.html"/>
   <updated>2012-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/06/16/picture-scanner</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Using a scanner is the best way to have picture with a high contrast and resolution. However, the speed of the acquisition is rather slow compared to a camera, specially if the resolution is high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spread your root carefully (A)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose a sufficient resolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/scanner.png&quot; alt=&quot;scanner&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the root system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scanning can be used with large root system as it is possible to separate the different root on scanner surface. It is important to carefully spread the root in order to avoid overlaps and crossing as much as possible. They are a nightmare for most of the root image analysis softwares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An easy way to separate the different root is to place the root system in a thin film of water. The roots will tend to recover their initial shape and they are easier to untangle as they float. This might require modify the scanner and to mount it on a specially design box (see image below).In order to avoid shadow around the roots floating in the water, a simple trick is to put a sheet of transparent paper on the spread roots. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the resolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before scanning the image most scanning software (if not, then it is a bad one) let you choose the resolution you want for your image. This resolution is often given in DPI, which stands for Dots Per Inch (even in countries using the metric system). In other words, a resolution of 300 DPI means that an inch on the image is represented by 300 pixels (or 118 pixels per centimeters). If you know the diameter of the roots you plan to scan you can therefore adapt the resolution of the scanner to your needs. For instance, if the smaller roots on your root system has a diameter of 0.1 mm and you scan it at 300 DPI, the diameter of these roots will be represented by 1-2 pixels, which is not enough for most image analysis software. You would need to increase the scanner resolution to have a image suitable for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/06/16/picture-scanner.html&amp;amp;text=Using a scanner to take root pictures&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cleaning root systems</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/06/16/cleaning-root.html"/>
   <updated>2012-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/06/16/cleaning-root</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you want to take a picture or scan a root system, one of the requirements is that this root system is clean of soil. While this is not an issue if the plant is grown in aeroponic or hydroponics, it is important for field- / pot-grown plants.The easiest way to clean roots is to simply let them soak in water, eventually with soap for several minutes. Then take them out and use pressurised water to remove the mud.If you need to clean smaller root or finer particles, you can use a brush to gently remove them from the roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/06/16/cleaning-root.html&amp;amp;text=Cleaning root systems&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using a camera to take horizontal root pictures</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/06/16/camera-horizontal.html"/>
   <updated>2012-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/06/16/camera-horizontal</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One way to take root picture using a camera is to put the root system on a flat surface and take picture from above. This technique is fast and can be used with large root system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a couple of things to think of before taking such image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose the proper camera and lens (A)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always place the camera at the same distance of the roots (B)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a dark, matt background (C)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place a scale on the background (D)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carefully separate the different roots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/camera_horizontal.png&quot; alt=&quot;horizontal camera&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the root system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique can be used with large root system as it is possible to separate the different root on the chosen surface. It is important to carefully spread the root in order to avoid overlaps and crossing as much as possible. They are a nightmare for most of the root image analysis softwares.An easy way to separate the different root is to place the root system in a thin film of water. The roots will tend to recover their initial shape and they are easier to untangle as they float. Be careful that using the camera flash on water will create  many reflexion. It is recommended to either remove the water once the roots are spread of the use indirect light (e.g. a spotlight directed a the ceiling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the camera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose a camera with a high-resolution. If the resolution if too low, the number of pixels contained in the roots will be too low to extract any information. In order to increase the resolution, it is also possible to take the picture closer to the roots, but his will need an adequate lens.&amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;About the background&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;Choose a background with a color different from the root (usually black is working well). Also be careful not the choose a “shiny” background, as it can create noise in the last image which can impedes the later analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;About the image scale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you take a picture with a camera, its scale (pixels/cm) will change if the distance between the object and the camera changes. It is therefore important that an object of a known size is present in the picture to scale your image during the image processing steps.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/06/16/camera-horizontal.html&amp;amp;text=Using a camera to take horizontal root pictures&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Acquiring root images</title>
   <link href="/perso//2012/06/16/Acquiring-root-images.html"/>
   <updated>2012-06-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2012/06/16/Acquiring-root-images</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The image acquisition step is a critical one as it will determine the quantity of information contained in the final image. Fortunately, good images can be obtain fairly simply without buying fancy expensive material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next posts I will give simple tips to acquire nice root images with either a CCD camera or a scanner (which are probably the most widely used image acquisition devices as well as the less expensive). But first a small reminder on the image requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Image requirement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous post I presented the main features required to have an image suitable for analysis. In short, the image has to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cleaned of the surrounding soil and dirt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;without too much root overlapping and crossing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;of high-resolution;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;highly contrasted (between the roots and the background)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scaled (number of pixels / cm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2012/06/16/Acquiring-root-images.html&amp;amp;text=Acquiring root images&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to choose the right root image analysis software</title>
   <link href="/perso//2011/12/06/choose-software.html"/>
   <updated>2011-12-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/2011/12/06/choose-software</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will try to point out the most important characteristics you will have to consider while choosing your root image analysis software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often, there is a strong link between an experimental design and the software used to treat the root images. Be careful that you should &lt;strong&gt;not be designing your experiment according to the available software&lt;/strong&gt; in your lab, but the other way round. As there is more and more available software, the field of possible analysis widens. Do not hesitate to** try different software** to find the one that suits your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The type of measurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just said, the software you will use to analyze your data will depend on your experiences needs. Check out &lt;strong&gt;which kind of measurement&lt;/strong&gt; is performed by every software before picking one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The raw image type and quality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the image type (jpg, tiff, …) and quality can restrict the number of potential root software you might use for your analysis. Some software can only open a &lt;strong&gt;limited number of image type&lt;/strong&gt; and most of them were designed for a &lt;strong&gt;specific kind of image&lt;/strong&gt; (scanned roots, mini-rhizotrons, …).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Free or commercial&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantage that &lt;strong&gt;commercial software&lt;/strong&gt; offers is a guarantee of &lt;strong&gt;quality&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;support&lt;/strong&gt;. As long as you pay for it, you will get something in return (at least in principle).It might seem obvious, but the advantage of &lt;strong&gt;free software&lt;/strong&gt; is that you &lt;strong&gt;do not pay&lt;/strong&gt; for them. This might be an important point as research teams do not always have money to buy costly products. Be aware that some &lt;strong&gt;freeware are built on commercial&lt;/strong&gt; frameworks such as Matlab. In this case, if you do not have this framework already installed on your computer, you will have to buy it before being able to install the desired freeware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;About quality:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exist some very good quality freeware that can compete with commercial ones. There is two ways you can check the quality of a freeware: you &lt;strong&gt;try it yourself&lt;/strong&gt; or you check if there is a &lt;strong&gt;scientific paper&lt;/strong&gt; describing the software and if &lt;strong&gt;other people are using it&lt;/strong&gt;. Just type the name of the software in the &lt;a title=&quot;ISI web&quot; href=&quot;http://isiknowledge.com/wos&quot;&gt;ISI database&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&quot;ISI web&quot; href=&quot;http://www.scopus.com&quot;&gt;Scopus&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com&quot;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt; to find it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;About support:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets face it, commercial softwares offer better user support than free ones. Freeware support often depends on the developer who might not even be working on that project anymore. And for specific software, a support team is often and advantage&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The degree of automation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can divide root analysis software according to their degree of automation (or user input, which is the exact opposite): &lt;strong&gt;fully automated&lt;/strong&gt;,** semi-automated &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; fully manual**.The ideal solution, especially if you have a lot of image to analyze, is obviously to choose a fully automated software. The perfect software would, indeed, allow you to choose any kind of measurement, load any kind of image and perform the analysis by itself. There is just one problem: this software does not exist (yet). Here are two reasons why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Actual automated analysis &lt;strong&gt;rely on the image kind&lt;/strong&gt;. They are often designed for one specific type of image (time-series, mini-rhizotron, …)
-Automated software often analyze a &lt;strong&gt;limited&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;number&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;of&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;variables&lt;/strong&gt; (length, diameter, …)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at all the available software, we can generally observe a &lt;strong&gt;trade-off between&lt;/strong&gt; their degree of &lt;strong&gt;automation&lt;/strong&gt; and their &lt;strong&gt;flexibility&lt;/strong&gt;.So if your &lt;strong&gt;images&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;needs match the requirements and capabilities&lt;/strong&gt; of an automated software, it will work great. If they do not match, these software might not be able to analyze you image and if they do, they might generate false results. In such case, you will have to choose a less automated solution.Even if you do not choose a fully automated solution, it is possible to &lt;strong&gt;limit the amount of work&lt;/strong&gt; during the analysis. Depending on the type of variable you want to retrieve, you can restrict the analysis to part of the image. As an example, it is possible to a have statistically significant estimation of† root diameters by looking at selected part of the root system. A global analysis is not always required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The portability of the data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are done analyzing your root images, it is important that you can use the generated data for &lt;strong&gt;further analysis&lt;/strong&gt;. The image analysis is often the very first step in the overall analysis pipe and if your software gives you useless data files, there is not point using it.In my opinion, you should be able to export you data to &lt;strong&gt;free standards&lt;/strong&gt; such as csv, txt or xml and not only to proprietary types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The user interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem stupid, but the user interface could be an important factor while choosing a software. If you plan to spend hours analyzing images, a crappy user interface† can quickly become counter-productive.The user interface as to be &lt;strong&gt;intuitive&lt;/strong&gt; (you do not want to search the correct button every time you want to perform an action) and &lt;strong&gt;efficient&lt;/strong&gt; (a sub-sub-sub-menu is not a right choice for an important tool). You might also want an interface having a nice design, but this is optional…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest constrain while choosing a root image analysis software is often the adequacy between the measurement you plan to make and the capabilities of the software. All the other constrains can be circumvent one way or an other. Just &lt;strong&gt;try out the different software&lt;/strong&gt; to found your perfect match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2011/12/06/choose-software.html&amp;amp;text=How to choose the right root image analysis software&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What makes a root image suitable for analysis?</title>
   <link href="/perso//2011/06/11/good-image.html"/>
   <updated>2011-06-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2011/06/11/good-image</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The quality of an image is central if you want to get useful information out of it. Even the best software will not be able to analyse crappy images, so it is crucial to think about what makes a good image and how to acquire it. Usually, you will have the opportunity to improve your images at different steps of the process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the growth of the plant (substrate, …)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the image acquisition (the type of devise)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the image preparation (thresholding,.. )&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the image analysis (the type of measurement, software)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/good-image-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image analysis pipeline&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; Image analysis pipeline&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;image-resolution&quot;&gt;Image resolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resolution of an images describe the details an image holds. It is often express as the number of pixels per surface unit. In the Anglo-Saxon system, the resolution is expressed in Dots Per Inch (DPI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/good-image-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The same object represented with different resolution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; The same object represented with different resolution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rule is that the greater the DPI value is, the more information is contained into the image. The drawback is that if you increase the resolution of your image, its size will also increase and it might get too large for manipulation and analysis (some software have a limit in the size of the image they can analyse).For root images, the &lt;strong&gt;optimal quality&lt;/strong&gt; of the image can be guested if you have an idea of the diameter of the root you want to analyse. This diameter, multiplied by the DPI value will tell how many pixels will be representing† your roots (if you work in cm, do not forget to divide the DPI by 2.54). This “&lt;strong&gt;pixel diameter&lt;/strong&gt;” will be the one ultimately influencing the image analysis processFor instance, a primary maize root, having a diameter of 0.1 cm, will be represented by 12 pixels if the image resolution is 300 DPI, 24 for 600 DPI and so on. In this situation, a 300 DPI image will be enough for your analysis.The image resolution is often determined by the type of devise you use to get your image (camera, scanner, …).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;image-contrast&quot;&gt;Image contrast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contrast of an image is the colour difference between the object you want to† analyse and the background of the image. This difference is important for the analysis software as it will allow it to separate the root objects from the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/good-image-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Images having different contrast between the root object and the background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; Images having different contrast between the root object and the background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For analysis purpose, the bigger the contrast is between the root and the background, the better the analysis will be.The contrast is generally defined by the image acquisition environment (your experimental set-up) but can also easily enhanced using some image manipulation techniques, as I will show in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;root-crossing-and-overlapping&quot;&gt;Root crossing and overlapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quality parameter which is specific to root image is the quantity of root crossing and overlapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/good-image-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example of root overlap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; Example of root overlap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If two roots are superposed on the image, it will not be possible any more to distinguish them and the information you will retrieve from the image will not be correct.Three strategies can be used to work around this issue.The first will be to carefully &lt;strong&gt;separate the roots&lt;/strong&gt; before you take the image in order to avoid any crossing or overlapping. This strategy is of course the better for the subsequent analysis but turns to be highly time consuming for mature root systems. More over, it is only applicable for scanner-type images and not for images of &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; root systems.Secondly, if you analyse the root system of &lt;strong&gt;young plants&lt;/strong&gt;, the reduced number and size of the lateral roots will prevent crossing and overlapping issues. This solution unfortunately constrain your experimental design.Finally, the third option will be to &lt;strong&gt;analyse only part of the image&lt;/strong&gt; in which the amount of root overlap is negligible. This strategies implies that you are not interested in global parameters (i.e. total root length), but in parameters that can be estimated locally (i.e. diameter or inter-branch distance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dirts&quot;&gt;Dirts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/good-image-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example of dirts in a root image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5.&lt;/strong&gt; Example of dirts in a root image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When root are not grown in systems such as aeroponics or agar, the image you will get might be full of dirt particles, on and around your roots.Again, these particles can distord you measurement such as root diameter or root number (for large dirt particles) so it is always better to get rid of them.Of course, the first way would be to &lt;strong&gt;clean your root&lt;/strong&gt; before the image acquisition step, but, as for the root separation it could be highly time consuming.Fortunately, as I will show in a future post, you &lt;strong&gt;image can be easily cleaned&lt;/strong&gt; from all the particles surrounding your roots. There is even some trick to get rid of the particles sticking to your roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-type-of-measurement&quot;&gt;The type of measurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, one major limitation to the type of image you wan use in your analysis is the type of measurement you plant to do on them.If you want to have &lt;strong&gt;global data&lt;/strong&gt; such as total root length and a detailed description of the architecture (connection, topology), the roots on the images will have to be perfectly separated and still all connected.On the other hand, if you only need &lt;strong&gt;variable that can be estimated locally&lt;/strong&gt;, such as root diameter of branching densities, the quality of your image can be lower and the time you will spend to prepare your roots before the acquisition will be highly decreased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2011/06/11/good-image.html&amp;amp;text=What makes a root image suitable for analysis?&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using thresholding method on root images</title>
   <link href="/perso//2011/05/15/thresholding.html"/>
   <updated>2011-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/2011/05/15/thresholding</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many root image analysis procedures have a thresholding step in their workflow (e.i. WinRHIZO or EZ-RHIZO). The thresholding step aims at segmenting the original image (fig. 1A) in two parts: the “object” (the roots) and the “background”, and to assign to each of them a different pixel value (typically 1 and 0). The subsequent binary image (fig. 1B) can be used, for instance, to generate a “root skeleton” (fig. 1C) or to estimate root diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/threshold_workflow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;threshold workflow&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/strong&gt; A. Original image. B. Binary image. C. Skeleton&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if &lt;strong&gt;thresholding&lt;/strong&gt; is a common image manipulation, it** has to be performed carefully** on root images. Indeed, the threshold value, defining the separation between the objects and the background, can have a great influence on the obtained binary image and therefore on the final results.Inappropriate threshold value can lead to a poor segmentation, typically “forgetting” the thinner roots (fig. 2B) or “creating” roots that are too large (fig. 2C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/threshold_diam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;threshold diameter&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; A. Original image. B. Threshold is too low, thinner roots where not selected. C. Threshold is too high, roots are too large&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How to choose a threshold value?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the threshold value influences the final results of the analysis it important the follow an identical methodology for the all the roots of the same experiment (or group of experiments). For this reason, it is not recommended to visually determine a threshold on every images as the human estimation could vary over time. It is also important that all the images of the same experiment have been acquired in the same conditions (light, devise, background, resolution, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/imagej_threshold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;imagej threshold&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; ImageJ thresholding window&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of analysis that has to be done at the end of the image processing also influences the choice of a threshold . The image requirement are not the same if you want to analyse root length (all the roots have to be on the image) or root diameter (root diameter has to be the same on the original and binary image).In ImageJ, thresholding an image can be achieved with the function &lt;span style=&quot;color: darkgrey;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image &amp;gt; Adjust &lt;/em&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Threshold&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. The threshold can then be set either manually or automatically with one of the implemented &lt;a title=&quot;Thresholding algorithm description&quot; href=&quot;http://fiji.sc/wiki/index.php/Auto_Threshold&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;thresholding algorithm&lt;/a&gt; (fig. 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Manual threshold&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manual threshold value can be used if the &lt;strong&gt;same value is used for all the images&lt;/strong&gt;. It can be evaluated on a typical (or several) image and then applied to all of them in the analysis workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Automatic threshold&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fiji.sc/wiki/index.php/Auto_Threshold&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Automated thresholding algorithms&lt;/a&gt; define a threshold value based on the image pixels statistics (mean, mode, histograms, etc). The use of such and algorithm might lead to different threshold values for the different images, but always based on an the same logic. For instance, visually thresholding the same image two days in a row might lead to different values while a predefined algorithm will choose always the same.As for the manual threshold, the choice of the appropriate algorithm has to be done on one or several typical images. This &lt;strong&gt;algorithm has to be applied to all the images&lt;/strong&gt; of the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0378429011000414&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent paper&lt;/a&gt;, Tajima and Kato have tested the different algorithms implemented in ImageJ to analysed scanned images of rice roots. Their conclusion was that the Triangle algorithm was the more appropriate for rice root images (compared to &lt;a title=&quot;WinRHIZO&quot; href=&quot;http://www.root-image-analysis.org/?p=160&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WinRHIZO&lt;/a&gt;). Here, I would like to quote &lt;a title=&quot;Pierre Soille&quot; href=&quot;http://isferea.jrc.ec.europa.eu/Staff/Pages/Soille.aspx&quot;&gt;Pierre Soille&lt;/a&gt; who said that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;...any non-specialist faced with an image analysis problem rapidly realises that a unique image transformation usually fails to solve it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that a single method, even if it is highly appropriate for a specific application, might not be good enough for slightly different usage. In this particular example, the Triangle algorithm works great with scanned root images having a good contrast, but is not optimal for images having an uneven background and a poor contrast…&lt;strong&gt;An algorithm has to be always validated on a specific image before using it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this post, you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?url=/2011/05/15/thresholding.html&amp;amp;text=Using thresholding method on root images&amp;amp;via=guillaumelobet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  share it with your followers&lt;/a&gt; 
or 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/guillaumelobet&quot;&gt;
  follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
